that yeah like Takashi 6:9 got arrested
or something but listen guys we've been
extra degenerate on these twitch streams
lately hang on me clear mystery I've
actually been working pretty hard lately
been slacking off less I'm in a
beautiful country this country's so good
they even have Japanese green tea and
roof down along the streams I have a
date at 7:30 but we're gonna try to be
less of a degenerate piece of like
we usually are on some of these streams
what up what up
so what context tree waiting is is you
guys can look this up so this is prized
called the hunter prize and basically
markets hunters assertion is that
compression is AI if you can build a
good compressor you can build by the way
this isn't related to the previous
project this is all new stuff maybe away
for a few more people and then and then
I'll do the eat the explanation of what
it is when we read this read this paper
using a context tree this method waits
in an efficient recursive way
um we put the FPGA thing I don't know I
wasn't feeling it as a project it would
take a long time she's a local to this
this lovely country but you know I've
been I've been less of a degenerate for
the last you guys known reading about
not context tree waiting in particular
but this is a fascinating paper
algorithmic theories of everything
should be Hooper solved AI guys like all
the stuff you'll need to know is here um
so you guys have you know there's a lot
of things in quantum physics that are
that are random that we you can't know
all you can do is model them
probabilistically but there's a question
of where that randomness comes from if
the universe the question is does our
universe have a short description or not
what's the column a graph complexity of
the universe for all we know there could
be a very simple PRNG
generating all of that randomness for
all we know it could literally be like a
es CTR one of these things we haven't
broken yet I'm an Aes CTR you can
specify really quickly so this is the
stuff I've been thinking about lately
being less of a degenerate was watching
some old streams like wack has
degenerate piece of drinking green
tea we're here in this beautiful country
and we'll talk quickly about how our
eyes compression I think this is gonna
be a theme of streams for now on because
this is something I'm actually excited
about the FPGA stuff it feels too much
like firmware head-fuck firmware that's
one of the things that I'm you know one
of the reasons I'm not back in the USA
ah
so I don't know what a context tree is
but there's this other paper I was
looking at as well called contracts tree
switching
a modification of contracts tree waiting
for the prediction of binary stationary
and Markov sources so I think everyone
knows what binary means binary just
means that it's a string of zeros and
ones right and all all text all images
can be can be put as a string of zeros
once stationary means that the
distribution doesn't change over time so
for example the great prize it's
referenced here is the hunter price the
hunter price is to take the first
hundred megabytes of Wikipedia and
compress it to be as small as possible
so I worked in my youth to try to win
this but it's pretty much been this guy
over and over again he's this Russian
guy and he writes this crazy code let's
download and McCade just so we can play
with them it's a good it's a good thing
to play with
I'm already
I think I also pay a bit too much
attention to the chat it's kind of hard
to see when it's on the phone I didn't
but we're being less of a degenerate on
these streams we're not gonna be a
degenerate you know you watch my auger
stream where I said working hard is not
important that's a lie
working hard for other people is not
important um you got to work on things
you care about and this is something
that I care a lot about I'm gonna be
working on it here and there so we've
selected we know what binary means
stationary means as opposed to non
stationary it means the distribution
stays the same it means any chunk of I
think the mathematical definition would
be any chunk of the distribution matches
any other chunk by any statistical test
you could do within some so Wikipedia is
a non-stationary distribution because
say you're in the article about durian
the word fruit is gonna be mentioned a
lot more because you're in the context
of Auckland area now I don't know what n
Markoff means um but what's interesting
about this context so that's context
tree waiting that's not this
modification um so here's the paper for
contracts tree waiting let's try to
understand ok find a memory resource of
property the next symbol probabilities
depending a finite number of most recent
symbols so you go this is called a
window for example if you're compressing
you can do a decent job compressing text
just by looking at like the previous two
letters I'm gonna be like like a tri
barium kind of thing
binary sequential universal source
coding procedures for finding which
besides of me
okay so what this is saying is after
you've seen like if you've seen 20 of
the same you have kind of a probability
but the next character is zero the
probability of the next character is one
so to put that in mathematical terms the
way you usually think of this is like
what's the probability of a 1 given
probability that X sub I equals equals 1
given X is zero X sub I minus 1 right
and then of course it's you know in this
binary that's the girl so given the
previous symbols now what this end
Markov I believe means that they talk
about in the other paper is this one it
really is kind of uncomfortable to work
on this laptop
I do need better I should use that more
I guess it's not bad as long as I don't
have too many windows open
[Music]
look at our Mexican zip so so Ann McKay
is video so thing and Markov is like how
many thing is you're going back run chat
on PC yeah but then I have to login to
touch on PC and we're not really doing
that this computer doesn't have any its
chaterino know what that is but don't I
probably respond to the chat too much
okay
so we can write a very simple compressor
that just behaves like that now it
doesn't necessarily need to be binary
you can of course do this where it's all
of ASCII but one of the problems with
that is you have you have rounding
errors right like you can you can make
you can make the symbol alphabet like
255 and you can track the probability
equals like you know one of each one of
the symbols but it's not very uh oh yeah
so the problems the problem is in the
binary one is very easy to do one - and
the other one is harder to do one - the
rest of them because it's a sum that's
just a problem that comes to my head
but yeah so let's just invite in the
enjoyment of actually writing a little
bit of code let's just make an wick six
so we can do this quickly in Python
since we're doing looks like binary or
stuff we're gonna use Python 2 so this
is a fun thing so let's see how well
like a normal compression algorithm
doesn't it looks X so yeah and works X
is one megabyte so that's just just an
idea of what Jesus juice is a two and
let's see if we can write a compressor
that beats gzip so once you have
probabilities it's trivial to well you
have something that can generate
probabilities of the probability the
next symbol you can turns into a
compressor perfectly by using this thing
called arithmetic coding forget that I
do not have chrome on this computer cuz
Google but we're not gonna dwell on
stupid like kugel anymore
because that's not what the streams
about I'm in a happy place I'm in a
beautiful country beautiful women
beautiful skyscrapers and malls and
green tea same should I add to Japan
right not exactly the cost more money
here surprisingly you think like all
yeah everything's so cheap but no no
that cost more money Dave in Japan
that's probably the only thing though
everything else is cheap
okay um so yeah I was gonna show you
guys quickly I threaded code into what
it is so if you're familiar with Huffman
coding - koenings not perfect Huffman
coding requires everything be aligned on
the bit arithmetic coding uses floats
yeah this is if you really want to
understand how to encode things like
that's the diagram that shows you maybe
we'll write a little arithmetic coder
we'll see how things go
can you please readjust what size and
OBS all the screen size yes I can't is
that better
[Music]
and you guys like where I am or should I
move myself somewhere else I'm probably
good there
all right cool the slaps Lipscomb you've
gotten so dirty and I haven't had a good
way to clean it so let's just write it
Jen fine you know what I should use
Python I should use bad my bad
so--but Jen is just going to 4 C of X Y
h8c once I shouldn't even need it all
right I don't know the command in Python
I want to do a take like instead of
writing this
what's important type for Astor imminent
it's not a star because I read it with
its bytes isn't it banks cuz I read it
with that that thing me Oh
my name is normal that's not right
[Music]
so that's returning false and true we
don't really want to return false and
trail so now we're getting zeros and
ones so we have a big stream of zeros
and ones these bit generators now so
let's um let's write a quick stupid
compressor just to get a baseline so
first let's
stop narration not fast at all right
let's make n with five let's even make
ever before you guys will get the idea
just 10 kilobytes
but if it's sick - so for reference we
need gzip and look for doesn't work oh
cool
you know you don't need the duct easy so
it for is just the first 10 kilobytes of
Wikipedia and when you gzip it it goes
down too fast out so if you want to
write something stupid we should be able
to use we'll use math I have to think
slower and use more math I understand
that's less entertaining but this
channel is not all about entertainment
it's about actually trying to publish
things useful things because we do
useful things on this channel
we're also or are we assholes I don't
know but yeah so
now if you want you can build a so we
can build something called lookup this
is the based idea of a lot of these sort
of compresses so we can have lookup be
you need a couple here yeah hook up some
three backs of one
okay so now for each lookup we get a
probability and this is the probability
that it's one so that's the probability
of the next bit given the previous four
bits so that's what we're talking about
here it's the probability that X of I
equals equals 1 given that well
especially not given that section so
this isn't context tree waiting yet I'm
still not exactly show a context tree
waiting guess it's gonna be something
kind of like this actually I don't even
need the x 1.0 because we're using
Python 3 yeah a time 5 of 3 is quicker
than Python - okay so the closer these
if these probabilities are 50% they give
you no information um if these
probabilities are more than 50% so now
what's the
okay
so let's call this P so assuming P of
one more 50%
let's check so what's the entropy
equated it's like the Shannon equation
so let me know how many bits the output
is yeah it's this PA is the probability
of a given symbol well
average number of minimum bits needed to
represent a symbol but that's not
exactly right
[Music]
how do I do log base sir good way to do
log those two in Python
other than way using change of base 100
is this another thing that's in Python 3
oh who loves Python 3 this guy oh look
I'm in such a good mood tonight I'm even
talking about my love for Python 3 no no
[Music]
ya hole so stream look we're not the
into generous anymore I'm in a good mood
we're in rapidly industrializing country
numbers
I'm gonna put the webcam back down in
its usual corner I don't think we're
doing anything interesting there it
looks like I'm back to coding over here
or something um okay so sure the entropy
P is the probability of a given symbol I
so I mean that's it's obvious that this
is true so this this if if you know
nothing
that works out all right so you know
probably the air you limp I know - the
one we know that - let's just try this
and see if this is right so that's the
entropy so that's without using any
predictor at all that's assuming that
every symbol has has equal likelihood
now that's the worst you can do if you
predict it all well math domain error
I'm getting that because I'm sure one of
them is zero
I guess the log at zero doesn't exist um
so this actually makes me think this is
there an equation oh there's also a
chance that well it's not even something
to take it to account again but you
can't use these directly as
probabilities the problem with using
these directly as probabilities is let's
initialize that to that okay there we go
that's better okay so okay all right
that's giving me an answer that's like
somewhat reasonable but okay the problem
zero is you start with a zero base rate
right so I get my I do my lookups and I
don't want to increment the tables
before I use them that's cheating
obviously don't cheat
okay so this is not answering the
question of how much the problem is it
doesn't take into account which the
symbol actually is which we know which
symbol X actually is if X if the
prediction is correct then it's going to
use less than 1 bits if the prediction
is wrong it's going to use more than 1
bits
[Music]
that's the
isn't right
hmm
well you know what okay no I might just
be - bass - that actually seems kind of
right if x equals equals one no I could
just say the probability of x equals I'm
so I can let you just say H equals -
math log to px that's actually that's
simple right let's do a quick check -
why that's true well I mean it makes
intuitive sense right if so this is
gonna be yeah you need less bits to code
that you need more bits to code that -
w-why is that true okay this make sense
right because if you were yeah so
there's gonna be half of it her no
have a bet okay
you'd one bit if you're half sure
because a bit of information see it's
hard to think in terms of but it is that
what is it log what an intuitive
understanding of why it's lock which I
said it's right why is it right
I've ridden an encoder before I think
someone come with a good intuitive
understanding of Wyatt's log I don't
know you people could on almost pretty
quiet a lesson you know so why is it
locked
yeah okay so you have your precision
where these are admitted coders work
because they they have precision they're
like infinite floats but they have
precision limits
well this is easier to think about
the opposite of log 2 is to to though
it's like to to the point log base 2 of
point 5 oh no so no the other way around
so that's that and then 2 raised to the
minus 1.0 is 0.5 how many bits
okay so this this this explains anything
if you have a set of if you have a set
of symbols obviously you need log number
of bits log two number of bits to encode
right if you have 256 possible symbols
you're gonna need log two of 256 to
encode them now what's interesting is
when you get into these these other
things you get it's it's just weird it's
weird to think about logs of things that
are less than one um I guess that's what
the log just makes less sense to me but
if you have 20 36 possible symbols your
way to so like a naive way to get that
out of yes so 1 divided by inside the
log is the same as doing that right so
you could also look at the probability
as you know 1 divided by the probability
and then you can take the log base 2 of
that because that's effectively how many
symbols you have to encode right god I
don't even remember like basic things
about logs how you forget math guys
don't forget ok so as you see this isn't
a very good compress we've managed to
take away 340 bytes
there's a lot of things we're doing
stupidly
on my roommates home let me say hi to my
roommate just so he doesn't think I'm
weird and talking to myself
[Music]
so I think I think I
yeah
[Music]
Oh
we just
Twiggy's do you hang out for that okay
let's look this place up
let's look up these Highlands and this
part this part will be chat um I'm not
there it's actually wrong I'm go look
for me all over Georgetown I'm up there
hi Lance
oh the Cameron highways
let's see well they have a golf club if
I only I play golf like it go
looks pretty pure Wow looks foggy all
cuz its high lands maybe the weather is
nice oh let's say I always do that all
reasonable temperature um this is a good
time for for trash-talking and chat if
anyone's paying attention
yeah now I was thinking of going to the
sidewall of a blank Aoi over here see
what the weather's like I'm going tally
there's no one talking the chatter is my
thing broken this is making noise which
is terrible no when Cowie weather looks
marginally better all talking checked it
easily broken on the twitch app they
have a concede oh ok I see you guys
talking now
wow so bad no one can talk only right at
Tom Cruise I see I see you all talking -
yeah Cameron Highlands oh I guess thanks
we go one of Malaysia's most popular
tourist destinations tourists no it's
just not scalding lehigh alright so I'll
tell you guys I'll tell you guys so this
is a massive City and none you will ever
be able to find me I'm in Kuala Lumpur
and it's oh it's just ninety degrees and
hot every day I wish there were
thunderstorms you don't even see any
thunder stories and hot um but I'm not
complaining because everything in my
life now is wonderful but yeah I'm
staying and I'm staying in a Airbnb like
thing my host showed up so as I was
talking with him that's that's where I
disappeared - yeah it's very hot what's
up the major now you'll never find me
here guys this place has more
skyscrapers
let's see let's go on booking and see if
there's reasonable places to stay in
this place
homestay I don't know about homestay I
don't think I can do homestay I like
this place I stayed in this apartment
for the last couple days
I'm gonna day later we'll see we'll see
it the uh no I don't know looks
expensive
Oh looks expensive good forget look at
that's expensive you guys oh no no what
do you mean that I believe that no one
talking to ignore you I'm watching you
talk I only have a 13 inch screen you're
in Tokyo you're gonna come to Malaysia
and vine me okay let's play a little bit
more with our compressor before we are
done with the stream so
[Music]
and actually you know we can really do
here it doesn't really matter
oh look at how much better it is when we
set it to eight bits look at that we're
compressing it all the way down to you
know we're getting a 72% compression
ratio but the thing about the number of
bits thing is it scales so like we do
that oh that seems to still work but if
we make it really huge it just won't
work
yeah so you can see the scales kind of
like oh you know what we should be good
about you can see what it looks like and
you can see that like the min of that
function is right down here at 16 it
bounces around a little bit but
makes sense
LZ SS are Li and Hoffmann yeah yeah
those are none of those compressors are
nearly as good as the ones that that
we're building I don't know what is all
zss um okay so it's like the vac
reference kind of stuff also like the
architecture for the uses of hunter
prize compressors see mix is a great one
if you want to read a good you want to
read a good loss that's what it looks
like this is basically predict the
probability distribution of next symbol
and then encode that probability
distribution with arithmetic use a
numerate where should I use a numerator
I love a new way it's one of my favorite
we're not gonna play with desc
now we can do better than this we can
actually do a mixture model now over the
different numbers of bits to initialize
it with the probability of 0.5 where
Kuala Lumpur
we're being honest this is a happy
stream I'm drinking green tea you know
when I'm drinking good tea I'm in a good
mood okay so we're still not beating
gzip we're still losing pretty badly to
gzip so gzip is getting it down to
thirty-seven point two eight and we're
getting it to fifty two point seven
seven nothing she's in seven so there
Jesus doing
compressing into thirty seven percent of
its size and we're compressing in 52
percent of its size so now let's see if
we can implement this context tree
waiting stuff so it's n markup so that
number of bits things the end that
they're talking about but I believe that
the way they do it it also works for
all like it's a mixture model of all of
those number of bits I had to go with 10
I got a shower I'm meeting this girl at
10:30 she rescheduled she said 10
we're rescheduling for 10:30 we'll see
okay number in general depends of the
ash without using symbols binary
sequential universal source coding
procedures for finite memory resources
also often make use of a context tree
which contains for each string the
number of zeros a number of ones that
have followed this context so that's
exactly what we're doing right there
we're not actually doing the number zero
as a number or ones we're doing the
number zeros in the number of total but
that's the same thing um how well does
an autoencoder work as compressor well
we can get to that kind of stuff so part
of the problem with using on neural
models as compressors is you have to
store the weights of your trained model
with your file so you lose a lot of the
stuff there unless you want to try
online training approaches I believe C
mix now which is the state of the art
compressor it's the state of the art
compressor the problem is it's extremely
slow but yeah I think I think there's an
LSTA em in their trap probability saw
leading to darkens
okay so
the standard approach given past our
symbols one uses this context tree debt
thank you for subscribing to assault one
model waiting techniques
what's model waiting techniques an
advantage of waiting procedures is that
they perform well not only on the
average but each individual see its
model waiting twice universal coding I
don't know what this stuff is founded
memory tree sources that allows
efficient updating okay
so this data structure I believe makes
sense right also alter egos are the same
suffix set are said to have the same
model a model and suffix that are
equivalent okay so I think I kind of see
where okay so they don't want to explain
our thematic Odin waited context ready
Happy's
so another common way to think about
these things is to realize that um every
single one of these is also a generator
right you if you have a probability
distribution especially if your source
is stationary you can just sample from
that and you will get things that look
indistinguishable from the sequence
there's some guy who does that there's a
guy who uses like pack eight as a text
generator I don't know where it is but
oh yeah it was that there generated
authentic text with pack thank you for
subscribing six-months lovely
pack for sentiment analysis data model
yeah so this is an example of random tax
generated by pack after compressing
Harry Potter
chapter 37 the Goblet of Lord Voldemort
of the fire bolt mayor um the text is
lower quality that I would say a lot of
our n ends could do it's pretty good the
stone Harry said battered the you said
Ron and Harry in the doorway come
whatever Hagrid was looking from
understood page so hardly to you said
Fred no in the morning they're not
enough we'll have all to her explain the
others had religious importance at
Dumbledore he wouldn't say anything
No
mostly two girls who have similar kind
of cultural backgrounds to me the high
school I went to is 40% Asian I mean
yeah if you if you understand you got to
know the mediums bra if you know the
same beams as me if you grew up reading
like 4chan and we'll get along too
bad not too many girls did that it's
tragic
okay so this is a weighted context tree
let's are these things computed unclear
there's no girls on 4chan I know guys
I'm not stupid sometimes what I find is
that the second paper so let's go back
to that other paper so I'm gonna find
that the papers that improve on things
actually explain the original thing I
don't know what that is actually explain
the original thing much better Oh
background waiting suppose we have a
finite set
[Music]
oh no no you just just you have the same
cultural background which will say who
knows who knows what we're gonna find
here in Malaysia Malaysia
the calendar context you waiting upon a
secret prediction technique it is
variable order Markov modeling technique
um so yeah if you guys know what Markov
means Markov means that just like so
traditional the traditional definition
of a Markovian sequence is that the
probability at you know X at time T
depends only on the probability of X of
T minus one and like that will
completely like it does not it's
independent with respect to X of t minus
two not a math guy understand my
notation is probably a little weird and
then so that's a first-order Markov
model you could have a second-order
Markov model where you know it depends
on X T minus 1 and XT minus 2 but then
it's independent of T minus 3 you know
be a second-order Markov so it's a
variable water market modeling technique
that works by computing a double mixture
over the space of all prediction suffix
trees of bounded depth this involves
weighting over all PST structures as
well as integrating over all possible
parameter values
No
Boxey
so um what we made what we made quickly
and our little compressor was just a uh
with my red just like this is a 16th
order Markov model on bits not on bytes
so it's really only 2 bytes no no look
okay yeah yeah Peters nice that I'm only
gonna answer this question once and
anybody else who asks they have to ask
that guy for the answer anyone who was
here today this is the answer of why I'm
traveling around I live in the world but
I want to live in the cloud you know
like AWS boxes you can't
what is the Colo for real life look like
that's maybe what I'm looking for I'm
not traveling around aimlessly and I'm
definitely not on a tour I go on
dates because this is something I do in
San Francisco as well you guys know I go
on dates in San Francisco I talk about
my dates on my stream um some of the
dates go well some of the days don't go
well you know but that's just the nature
of Danny um I met some digital nomads I
would not call myself a digital nomad uh
I want to move yeah the Colo for real
life instead of traveling or vacation I
prefer the word quest is that
pretentious or what I'm on a quest to
find and move to the cloud
okay we all happy with that hey I got a
go I got a I got a shower but we will we
will this will be this will be our new
project for a little bit and we'll go
hard on this we're good we're gonna
implement context tree waiting and maybe
even context tree switching yes I want
to live in the cloud I am on a quest to
find and move to the cloud perfect
that's that's a good way to summarize it
and I want all the great features that
the cloud offers you know I want to have
backups I want to have multi data set of
redundancy I want to have super high
bandwidth internet connections one of
peter levels I don't know what Peter
levels are that was too much philosophy
oh sorry
yeah we're gonna we're gonna get back
we're gonna we're gonna be I want you to
remember on the stream I'm from here on
out this is gonna be less of a
degenerate stream I don't really want to
do the FPGA thing anymore I was boring
me I was just dealing with like you saw
use of that stream where I spent like an
hour just dealing with like docker
comes up nomad list today you guys ever
gonna know that list I also found this
other web said I really liked called
hood maps
no hood maps is great like you know
Creek gecko wannabes Chinese med playing
chess some of them were really good I
was looking at Severns this infinite
tourists crack my thoughts up into that
crack McDonald
um yeah nomads lost places too maybe is
Kangoo bali the cloud it's Bangkok
Thailand the cloud no but they're like
these people like oh yeah but digital
nomads oh yeah look I'm buying I'm
buying Chinese cosmetic products and
then I'm selling them two white girls on
Etsy Oh Peter levels Oh No I don't know
oh that's the guy who made this website
oh oh yeah
but he also made hood maps no I really
wasn't joking I had no idea I didn't
even realize just the same guy this
guy's awesome
are you twitchy's teach me so much
Wow
wow this guy is he moved to the cloud he
did it
does that are you a subscriber why do
you have a crown your twitchy's no
actually scope ease and twitch ease or
copyright comma AI I can't say them
anymore
Wow I'm gonna read more about this Peter
levels guy where is he
crownless twitch Prime you're okay
why can't you be chat you guys you guys
are twitchy's all right um wow you want
to be chat you also coated what maps one
stream no no I can't be this guy I don't
want to go to the cloud if this guy's
already there no yeah she seems pretty
cool um alright thank you for joining my
stream today we'll work harder next
dream because we would have date
schedules drifter date sucks maybe I'll
just come back here quickly
maybe she'll flake I think she'll fly no
I think she looks like JavaScript back
all right see you later